{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man’s willingness to testify as a character witness convinced a judge to drop an anti-Communist trial against W.E.B. Du Bois. This scientist’s namesake field equations can be used to calculate spacetime geometry and includes the cosmological constant, which is referred to as this scientist’s “biggest blunder.” In1952,thisscientistwasofferedthepresidencyofIsrael.Fortenpoints,namethisscientistwhodeveloped the theory of relativity and the equation E equals m c squared.",
      "answer": "Albert Einstein"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the build-up to this case, Shirley Wheeler was arrested and charged with manslaughter. This case, decided at the same time as Doe v. Bolton, was eventually opposed by its own plaintiff who had converted to Catholicism. Norma McCorvey brought forth this case whose aspect of fetal viability was reaffirmed in Casey v. Planned Parenthood. For ten points, name this 1973 court case that legalized abortions.",
      "answer": "Roe v. Wade"
    },
    {
      "question": "This political party’s principles were outlined in the Tamworth Manifesto, written by Robert Peel as a way to separate his policies from those of his ally, the Duke of Wellington. A modern leader of this party took power after the “Winter of Discontent,” replacing James Callaghan in 1979. For ten points, name this British political party whose members, like Margaret Thatcher, are commonly known as “Tories.”",
      "answer": "Conservative and Unionist Party"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man started his first company with Henry Flagler but later grew his own enterprises after absorbing his competitors in the Cleveland Massacre. Ida Tarbell exposed the unethical business practices of this man in a work published in McClure’s. The Sherman Antitrust Act broke up this man’s company, ultimately resulting in the formation of companies like Chevron and Exxon. For ten points, name this all-time richest American who founded Standard Oil.",
      "answer": "John Davison Rockefeller"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a festival celebrating this god on Mount Mycale [my-kuh-lee], a high priest ritually appointed a young man “King of Priene.” This god supposedly gave Peleus, the husband of Thetis, two immortal horses named Balius and Xanthus that were later passed down to Achilles. This god competed with Athena over the patronage of Athens, losing after she gave an olive tree. For ten points, name this Greek god of the sea.",
      "answer": "Poseidon"
    },
    {
      "question": "If not soaked in alkali water, depending on this staple crop can cause pellagra through Vitamin B 3 deficiency. In Mesoamerica, archaeologists can tell which people were city-dwelling versus rural-dwelling by whether their teeth show cavities from eating this crop. With squash and climbing beans, this crop is part of the “Three Sisters” of agriculture in North America. For ten points, name this cereal grain that is also known as maize.",
      "answer": [
        "corn",
        "maize before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In the ground portion of this campaign, the London Irish Rifles captured four soldiers in the Battle of the Graveney Marsh. The failure of this campaign led one side to cancel Operation Sea Lion, a planned amphibious invasion. In response to this campaign, Winston Churchill praised the pilots of the Royal Air Force. The Blitz attacks on London followed, for ten points, what air campaign against Great Britain carried out by Nazi Germany?",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Britain",
        "The Air Battle for England",
        "Luftschlacht um England"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A 2016 mass shooting of police in this city ended when a robot delivered a bomb to this city’s El Centro College. Officer JD Tippit was shot and killed in this city shortly after another shooting that took place in this city’s Dealey Plaza. For ten points, name this city where a Texas School Book Depository was the staging point for Lee Harvey Oswald’s assassination of John F. Kennedy.",
      "answer": "Dallas"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this novel, Cassy and Emmeline escape to Canada, where Cassy is reunited with her grandson, Harry, and her daughter, Eliza. Ophelia and Topsy are united by the death of Little Eva in this novel, before Augustine St Clare’s death leaves his wife free to sell the title man to Simon Legree. For ten points, name this novel by Harriet Beecher Stowe that, legend says, Abraham Lincoln credited with beginning the Civil War.",
      "answer": [
        "Uncle Tom’s Cabin",
        "or, Life Among the Lowly"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "While contesting power over Silk Road cities in the Fergana Valley, this empire defeated the Tang Dynasty at the River Talas. A ruler of this empire gifted Charlemagne both an elephant and a water clock that perplexed his court. This empire, which was later centered in Mamluk Egypt, had its capital sacked in the 13th century by Hulagu Khan. For ten points, name this empire that built Baghdad and succeeded the Umayyads.",
      "answer": "Abbasid Caliphate"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was mocked by the press for being attacked by a “killer rabbit” while fishing in a swamp. In an interview for Playboy, this man admitted that he had “committed adultery” in his heart “many times.” This man stated that America was facing a “crisis of confidence” in his Malaise speech, which focused on the on-going energy crisis. The Iran Hostage Crisis hurt the approval rating of, for ten points, what President who lost the Election of 1980 to Ronald Reagan?",
        "answer": "James “Jimmy” Carter"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Jimmy Carter was “attacked” by a rabbit while fishing in this state, where he had served as governor from 1971 to 1975.",
        "answer": "Georgia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The losers of this battle suffered from Quintus Dellius defecting and giving their battle plans to the enemy. The smaller and quicker Liburnian ships fought against a smaller force of quinqueremes near the Ambracian Gulf in this battle. The victory of Marcus Agrippa at this battle allowed a leader to take the title “Princeps” and usher in the Roman Empire. For ten points, name this 31 BC naval battle in which Augustus defeated Marc Antony and his Egyptian allies.",
        "answer": "Battle of Actium"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Marc Antony was supported by this ruler of Egypt who, after the battle, legendarily killed herself with an asp bite.",
        "answer": "Cleopatra VII Philopator"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of this composer’s works was re-arranged for use as the anthem of the UEFA [you-ay-fah] Champions League; that work, Zadok the Priest, has been used for the coronation of every English king since George II. This man helped commemorate the signing of the Treaty of Aix-la-Chapelle in his Music for the Royal Fireworks. For ten points, name this composer whose oratorio Messiah includes the Hallelujah chorus.",
        "answer": "George Frederick Handel"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Handel’s Music for the Royal Fireworks was written to celebrate the Treaty of Aix-la-Chapelle and the end of this war in 1748.",
        "answer": "War of the Austrian Succession"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this election year, Shepard Fairey made a poster of the winning candidate in solid red, beige, and blue. One candidate in this election year called his opponent “a decent family man” after an audience member labeled that opponent “an Arab.” The winning candidate in this year used the slogan “Yes We Can,” and ran with Delaware senator Joe Biden. For ten points, name this election year in which John McCain lost to Barack Obama.",
        "answer": "US presidential election of 2008 BONUS:ThisformergovernorofMassachusettsfinishedwiththethirdmostdelegatesaftertheRepublican primaries in 2008. He later became the Republican presidential candidate in 2012. ANSWER: Willard “Mitt” Romney 5 In the aftermath of this battle, the body of the winning commander was stored in a barrel of brandy for transport. The flagship of Admiral Collingwood, the Royal Sovereign took heavy damage in this battle. A commander in this battle signaled “England expects every man to do his duty” after he drove his ships towards a French fleet. Horatio Nelson was killed in, for ten points, what 1805 battle off the coast of Spain that Britain won? ANSWER: Battle of Trafalgar"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Horatio Nelson died aboard this vessel, his flagship.",
        "answer": "HMS Victory"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A massacre of these people was uncovered in the Sidr´on Cave system in Spain, indicating that cannibals ate the 15 dead. These people were fully wiped out during a very cold period of European history 40,000 years ago. This species, named for a valley in Germany, share 1 to 2 percent of its DNA with Homo sapiens. Prominent brows are a notable feature of, for ten points, what cave-dwelling hominid species?",
        "answer": "Neanderthals or Homo neanderthalis"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Neanderthals are named for the Neander Valley, which is formed by a tributary of this major west German river. Nazi Germany violated the Treaty of Versailles in March 1936 by re-militarizing the land around this river.",
        "answer": [
          "Rhine",
          "Rhine River",
          "Rhineland"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A blockade ordered by this man was circumvented when Israeli operatives smuggled ships out of Cherbourg Harbor. Lester Pearson said “Canadians do not need to be liberated” after this man exclaimed “Long live free Quebec.” This politician signed the Evian Accords, granting independence to Algeria. The May 1968 student protests forced this man to temporarily flee Paris. For ten points, name this French President who led Free French forces during World War II.",
        "answer": "Charles de Gaulle BONUS:Inhisbook,The Army of the Future,CharlesdeGaulleheavilycriticizedthislineoffortifications, which were circumvented by German troops at the start of World War II. ANSWER: Maginot Line 8 This thinker developed a phonetic alphabet that abandoned so-called “redundant letters” such as “c, j, q, w, x, and y.” Letters from Thomas Hutchinson about cracking down on Bostonians were deliberately leaked by this man. This politician was appointed the first United States Postmaster General by the Continental Congress. For ten points, name this Pennsylvanian founding father who flew a kite during a lightning storm. ANSWER: Benjamin Franklin"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Benjamin Franklin published this almanac under a pseudonym he stole from Rider’s British Merlin.",
        "answer": "Poor Richard’s Almanac"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Richard Nixon",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Asian country where he met Zhou Enlai in Beijing.",
          "answer": [
            "People’s Republic of China",
            "Zhongguo"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Scandal that led him to resign, named for a Washington office building.",
          "answer": "Watergate scandal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pacifistic religion of which he was a member.",
          "answer": [
            "Quakers",
            "Religious Society of Friends"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Democrat from Massachusetts who defeated him in the Election of 1960.",
          "answer": "John Fitzgerald Kennedy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former Vice President who controversially pardoned him.",
          "answer": [
            "Gerald Ford",
            "Leslie Lynch King"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Soviet leader with whom he argued in the Kitchen Debate.",
          "answer": "Nikita Khrushchev"
        },
        {
          "question": "State where he competed against Helen Gahagan Douglas for a Senate seat in 1950.",
          "answer": "California"
        },
        {
          "question": "1952 speech, named for the family dog, that he gave defending himself against accusations of misusing funds.",
          "answer": "Checkers speech"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Anti-Semitism",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Water source Jews were often accused of poisoning.",
          "answer": "wells"
        },
        {
          "question": "Banking family started by Mayer Amschel whose massive wealth led to anti-Semitic conspiracies.",
          "answer": "Rothschild"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sectioned-off parts of cities where Jews were forced to live, as in Nazi-controlled Warsaw.",
          "answer": "ghetto"
        },
        {
          "question": "November 1938 event in which Jewish businesses were destroyed in one night in Nazi Germany.",
          "answer": [
            "Kristallnacht",
            "Night of Broken Glass"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for a campaign in which Jews or other minorities are massacred, particularly as in the Pale of Settlement.",
          "answer": "pogrom"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that established the Pale of Settlement.",
          "answer": "Russia"
        },
        {
          "question": "French-Jewish army officer who was the center of a political affair in France after being wrongly arrested.",
          "answer": "Alfred Dreyfus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Myth that Jews were responsible for Germany’s defeat in World War I.",
          "answer": "stab-in-the-back myth"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "World War II in Asia",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country that started the fighting by invading China in 1937.",
          "answer": "Japan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Peninsula that was subject to strict rule from a puppet government in Seoul.",
          "answer": "Korean Peninsula"
        },
        {
          "question": "Region of China that was turned into a puppet kingdom under Pu Yi.",
          "answer": [
            "Manchuria",
            "Manchukuo"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City-state founded by Stamford Raffles that was besieged.",
          "answer": "Singapore"
        },
        {
          "question": "Island where American troops raised a flag on Mount Suribachi.",
          "answer": "Iwo Jima"
        },
        {
          "question": "1942 naval battle that resulted in the destruction of the USS Lexington.",
          "answer": "Battle of the Coral Sea"
        },
        {
          "question": "1944 battle off the coast of the Philippines, possibly the largest naval battle in history.",
          "answer": "Battle of Leyte Gulf"
        },
        {
          "question": "Northern Australian city that was bombed by Japanese forces in February 1942.",
          "answer": "Darwin"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Ice nearly prevented Henry Knox from completing this action with 18 artillery pieces. Shortly before this action took place, Thomas Paine’s The American Crisis was read to a group of men whose enlistment ended on (20 pts)",
        "Christmas. An 1851 Emanuel Leutze [LOYT-zuh] painting shows James Monroe standing and Nathaniel Greene leaning over the edge of a (10 pts)",
        "boat while performing this action. The Battle of Trenton followed, for ten points, what military movement undertaken at night by Washington’s Revolutionary Army in December 1776?"
      ],
      "answer": "George Washington and/or the Continental Army crossing the Delaware River"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader fabricated the “Doctors” Plot” in order to arrest political enemies. The Holodomor was likely organized by this leader to reduce the population of the (20 pts)",
        "Ukraine. The New Economic Policy was rejected by this leader, who instead implemented five-year plans. This man ordered the (10 pts)",
        "NKVD to carry out the “Great Purge,” which left the Red Army unprepared to deal with an eventual German invasion. For ten points, name this “man of steel” who led the Soviet Union through World War II."
      ],
      "answer": "Joseph Stalin"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A member of this order, Alessandro Valignano, delivered Yasuke to Japan where he later became a samurai under Oda Nobunaga. This order was allowed to use the port of (20 pts)",
        "Dejima in Nagasaki to carry out trade. This order, which was created near the start of the (10 pts)",
        "Counter-Reformation, sent Matteo Ricci to Macau to start converting the Chinese. Ignatius of Loyola founded, for ten points, what Christian order also known as the Society of Jesus?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Jesuits",
        "Society of Jesus before it is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this event, John Richards warned his congregation against a reliance on spectral evidence. A man executed by pressing during this event demanded (20 pts)",
        "“more weight” rather than plead guilty. Giles Corey was killed during this event, which started when (10 pts)",
        "Sarah Good, Sarah Osborne, and Tituba were arrested for causing two girls to go into epileptic fits. For ten points, name this 1692 event in which over a dozen women were executed for allegedly practicing magic in a Massachusetts town."
      ],
      "answer": "Salem Witch Trials"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) According to William Julius Wilson, this concept’s importance is declining due to the complex nature of job markets. In The Bell Curve, Charles Murray linked differences in intelligence to this concept. “One (20 pts)",
        "drop” rules have been used to classify this concept, and (10 pts)",
        "poll taxes and literacy tests were used in the Jim Crow South to discriminate based on this concept. For ten points, name this sociological concept that may be divided on census forms into types like black, white, and Asian."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "race",
        "ethnicity"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this election year’s primaries, a conservative politician was labeled “wife stealer” after marrying the recently divorced Happy Murphy. One side in this election year parodied their opponent’s campaign slogan with the phrase (20 pts)",
        "“In your guts, you know he’s nuts.” During this election year, an (10 pts)",
        "ad showed a small child picking the title flower before a nuclear explosion. The Daisy ad aired during, for ten points, what election year in which Barry Goldwater was defeated by Lyndon B. Johnson?"
      ],
      "answer": "Election of 1964"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A war in this country centered around Villmergen led to the annihilation of a religious community in Schwyz [SHVOOTZ]. Catholics and Protestants in this country clashed in the (20 pts)",
        "Kappel Wars. Ulrich Zwingli brought Anabaptism to this country. This country was the site of the (10 pts)",
        "Sonderbund War, in which regions like Valais and Lucerne allied to fight against centralized authority. For ten points, name this country where John Calvin spread his teachings while living in Geneva."
      ],
      "answer": "Switzerland"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A farcical game involving naming sections of this system is named for the ostensible winning play, “Mornington Crescent.” The font Johnston was developed for this system’s use, as seen in its (20 pts)",
        "red roundel logo. Harry Beck designed an iconic map of this system that looks like a scar above Albus (10 pts)",
        "Dumbledore’s left knee. SAS agents fight terrorists who have hijacked a train in this system in a Call of Duty level named “Mind the Gap.” For ten points, name this fourth-longest mass transit system in the world, which started serving London in 1863."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "London Underground",
        "descriptive answers of London’s subway system",
        "prompt on “the Tube",
        "”"
      ]
    }
  ]
}